Mary Jeffries Bruce and the Sunday Evening Forum collection, 1942-1993
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Mary Jeffries Bruce and the Sunday Evening Forum collection1942-1976
Mary Jeffries Bruce and the Sunday Evening Forum collection
MS 472
Jeffries, Mary Bruce
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
The collection consists of personal scrapbooks created by Mary Jeffries Bruce who was the director of the Sunday Evening Forum in Tucson, Arizona from 1942-1976. The 21 scrapbooks contain photographs, correspondence and newspaper articles chronicling the national and international prominent people who spoke at the Forum. They also contain personal correspondence and information regarding Ms. Bruce’s longtime work with the National Association for Mental Health, and a bound collection of letters written by previous guests of the Forum given to Ms. Bruce upon her retirement.
3 linear feet
Restrictions
None
Biographical Note
Mary Jeffries Bruce was born in Clinton, Kentucky and raised in Tennessee. She attended Peabody College in Nashville where she majored in Art and then Voice. Ms. Bruce taught school in Paris, Tennessee. She moved to Tucson in 1930 where she married V.T. Jeffries and became the mother of John Edgar. In 1942 she was appointed program chairman for a small Young Adult Discussion Group which met in the old University Catalina Methodist church (now known as the Catalina United Methodist Church). This small discussion group became The Sunday Night Forum and one of the nation’s largest nonprofit community forums under her leadership. The Forum grew and ultimately moved to a larger venue, University of Arizona Main Auditorian. At first the guest speakers were famous people wintering in Tucson or local notables, especially members of the University of Arizona faculty Auditorium. By 1945 the guest speakers included political leaders and some world renowned persons. Besides famous speakers, the forum also presented travel films, nationally known dance groups, theatrical groups, and musical groups. After 42 years as a Tucson institution the Sunday Evening Forum gave its final performance on April 8, 1984. The board of the Catalina United Methodist Church decided to discontinue the Forum at the end of 1983/84 season. The board had sponsored the forum since it began in 1942. The closure was attributed to high speaker fees, lack of interest by the public, and finally the announcement by the University of Arizona that the Main Auditorium would not be available for the next season of the forum while it underwent renovation. In 1952 Mary Jefferies Bruce was named Tucson’s 1st "Woman of the Year" for her work as director of the Sunday Night Forum. In 1969 she received the "Program Chairman of the Year" award, presented by the International Platform Association. Ms. Bruce was responsible for bringing many of the most prominent political and cultural figures of the time to Tucson. Ms. Bruce directed the Sunday Night Forum for 34 years before retiring in 1976. In her lifetime, Mary Jeffries Bruce was very active in the National Association for Mental Health and was voted a regional vice president serving on the National Executive Committee in 1954. She was also a past president of the Tucson’s Boys Choir ,1949-1950, and arranged for the Chorus to sing at the New York Town Hall. Ms. Bruce was also the volunteer Executive Secretary for The Pima County Mental Health Association. She passed away on February 7, 1993 at the age of 89.
Arrangement
This Collection is organized into 2 series.>
Series I: Albums, 1942-1976
Series II: Retirement booklet, 1976
Series III: Oleg Kirillov materials, 1960-1993
Access Terms
Sunday Evening Forum (Tucson, Ariz.) - History.
Forums (Discussion and debate)-Arizona.
Catalina United Methodist Church (Tucson, Ariz.)-History.
Tucson (Ariz.)-Church history.
Bruce, Mary Jeffries.
Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.
King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968..
Goldwater, Barry M. (Barry Morris), 1909-1998.
Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006..
Buckley, William F. (William Frank), 1925-2008.
Reasoner, Harry, 1923-1991.
Udall, Morris K.
Udall, Stewart L..
Container List
- Series I: Albums, 1942-1976
  This series is arranged chronologically by album. The albums correspond to the Sunday Evening Forum season. Each album contains photographs, newspaper clippings, and correspondence. The bulk of the materials are newspaper articles either announcing the forum speakers or about the speakers. There is also some documentation of Mary Jefferies Bruce work with the National Association for Mental Health.
  - Album 1, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Content Note
    1942-1943 Season. Some of the speakers included in this season were: Hugo W. Wolter assistant director of the Japanese Relocation camp located at Rivers, Arizona; Ruth McKenney an American author and journalist, best remembered for My Sister Eileen; Kirby Page an American Disciples of Christ minister, an author, and a peace activist. Also among the speakers were educators, employees of the U.S. Consular Service, a missionary, and an army corps nurse who escaped by submarine from Bataan
    1944-1945 Season. Notable speakers for this season were: Clarence Streit, author of “Union Now”. Charles P. Eisenmayer national president of the Gideon’s the famous bible-distributing organization; Rosemary Drachman Taylor, Tucson author of “Chicken Every Sunday”; Mrs. Margaret Sanger Slee leader of the Planned Parenthood movement; Madame Vijaya Laksmi Pandit sisiter of Jawaharal Nehru Nationalist leader of India
    1945-1946 Season. The first speaker for this season was William R. Mathews, editor and publisher of the Arizona Daily Star. Other speakers included: H.R. Knickerbocker a Pulitzer Prize Journalist and foreign correspondent; Kumar Goshal author of the “People of India”.
  - Loose items, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Album 2, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    1946-1947 Season began with John Boettigers and his wife Anna Roosevelt Boettigers both editors and publishers of the Arizona Times. Other lecturers include: Mr. Clifford Goldsmith creator of radio’s famous Henry Aldrich; Pastor Martin Niemoeller who spent 7 years in a Nazi concentration camp for defying Hitlerism; Godfrey Winn a well-known journalist who spoke on “Life Begins in England Again”; Miss Myrtle Ross a mono-dramatist ended the season with a Mother’s Day program.
    1947-1948 Season opened with Carveth Wells an explorer, radio commentator, and author who gave a travel talk on “Travel and Laugh with Carveth Wells”. Other speakers were: Louis P. Lochner a Pultizer Prize winner and chief of the Bureau of the Associated Press in Berlin until 1942; Congressman Richard F. Harless from Arizona spoke on “World Reconstruction Peace or War”. Marquis Childs a syndicated columnist, author of the daily column “Washington Calling” his topic for the forum was “America Must Choose”; Lady Nancy Longhorn Astor talked before the largest crowd of the season, her talk was entitled “My Two Countries”.
  - Loose items, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Album 3, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    1948-1949 Season was launched with a lecture by Dr. Che Shou-Yi. The title of his address was “The Significance of the China Crisis” which reported on the current conditions in China. Other speakers included: Howard Pyle radio commentator and station manager of KTAR in Phoenix. Pyle’s subject was “The Place of Education in Tomorrow’s World”; Raymond Swing a radio commentator and news analyst spoke on the topic “History on the March” and called for the need of a world law and government; Ms. Dorothy Thompson author, radio commentator, and columnist spoke on the disintegration of Europe and the present world crisis, her topic was “These Crucial Days”.
    1949-1950 Season’s first speaker was Sidney Lawson a worldwide traveler whose topic was “India As I See it”. Arizona Senator Ernest McFarland discussed the Colorado River water controversy, suspension of copper tariffs and legislation dealing with the Navajo and Hopi Indians and how these issues would affect Arizona. Stuart Chase a noted author and commentator on economic and social problems gave a lecture on “Boom or Bust? Can We Smooth the Business Cycle?”. Dr. Paul Popenoe director of the American Institute of Family Relations in Los Angles was the final speaker of the 1949/50 Sunday Night Forum season. He discussed “Making Marriage a Success” by understanding of one’s self, partner and of marriage it itself.
  - Loose items, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Album 4, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    1950-1951 Season started with the well-known educator Frank C. Laubach who founded the “Each One Teach One” system of teaching reading and wiping out world illiteracy. Other speakers for the season were: Cecil Brown a radio commentator whose topic was “Cross fire in Asia”. Mr. Brown was introduced by Ronald Reagan who happened to be filming a movie in Tucson at the time; Senator Margaret Chase Smith from Maine the only woman to serve in both the House of Representatives and the Senate. Her lecture was titled “Report from Washington. The final presentation of the 1950-51 season was with Mayan explorers Dana and Ginger Lamb. They gave an illustrated travel talk entitled “The Lost City of the Mayas”. The story was told in words and by color movie. They explained why they took a 3 year trip in a 16 foot canoe from San Diego to Panama.
    1951-1952 Season began with Dr. Pearce Hayes a missionary in China for over 30 years, director of the Fochow Mission and executive secretary of the International Relief committee. He discussed “Bamboo Screen or Iron Curtain in China”. Other speakers for the season were; Senator Estes Kefauver from Tennessee was the originator and chairman of the senate’ crime investigation committee; William O. Douglas associate justice of the U.S. Supreme Court presented a lecture on his recent travels to the Middle East exploring both the back country and the cities. The lecture was titled “Asia and the Middle East”; Dr. Margaret Mead, a distinguished anthropologist and associate curator of ethnology at the American Museum of Natural History in New York presented “Cultural Conflicts in World Unity”. The final speaker for the season was Bishop S.K. Mondol of Hyderabad who spoke on the topic of “India since Her Freedom”.
  - Loose items, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Album 5, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    1952-1953 Season. The 1st speaker was Bishop Gerald Kennedy head of the Los Angeles area of the Methodist church. He spoke the subject “The Church and Contemporary Issues.” Other notable speakers for the season were: Earl Warren one of only two people to be elected Governor of California three times. His topic for the Sunday Night forum in 1952 was “Problems of the “Southwestern States” in which he discussed California’s water shortage and its need of Colorado River water; Governor Howard Pyle made his 8th consecutive appearance at the forum and He spoke on the subject of “How Firm are Arizona’s Foundations”; the final speaker for the 1952-1953 season was Commander Irving M. Johnson presented the film “Join the Yankee and See the World”.
    1953-1954 Season. Senator J. William Fulbright of Arkansas spoke to the forum on the topic “The United States in World Affairs”. Senator Fulbright is known for his work in establishing scholarship foundations based on funds received from by the U.S. in the sale of surplus property abroad. Claude Rains a well-known actor of stage and screen gave dramatic readings from Chaucer to T.S. Eliot. His program was called “Great Words to Great Music” and was performed before a capacity crowd. Mrs. Eleanor Roosevelt spoke on “The United Nations Today”. Mrs. Roosevelt was a United States representative to the UN General Assembly from 1945 to 1952 and in 1946 became the chairman of the UNESCO committee on human rights. Chet Huntley radio commentator and news analyst gave a talk on “Our Foreign Policy Today”. The last performer of the 1953-1954 Sunday Forum was Kathryn Turney Garten who returned for her 17th appearance. Her subject was a dramatization of “The Bible as Living Literature”.
  - Loose items, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Album 6, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    1954-1955 Season. Notable speakers were: Senator Barry Goldwater of Arizona. He gave an analysis of the “new look” in America’s Air Force calling it the greatest power for peace and that it was built for peace; Oveta Culp Hobby was the first secretary of the United States Department of Health, Education and Welfare and the only woman member of the Eisenhower cabinet. She spoke on issues facing our country as seen through her department; Dr. Norman Vincent Peale American church leader and writer. Dr. Peal told Tucsonans to “End Worry --- Live Longer”; The Dublin Players of the Abby Theater Group appeared in two Irish plays “The Far Off Hills” and “ Pygmalion”; Yew Char, lecturer, photographer, and former member of the Hawaiian legislature, spoke and showed films of the Hawaiian Islands.
    1955-56 Season. 1st term Representative Stewart Udall of Arizona spoke on “The Need for New Maturity in Public Life”. Sylvia Porter, financial editor, of the New York Post topic was “The Brain has no Sex”. Henry Hull was an American character actor presented “An evening with Mark Twain”. Jackie Robinson Brooklyn Dodger star and the first African American player in organized baseball talked to the forum about his career. Dr. Douglas M. Kelley a U.S. Army Intelligence officer who served as Nuremberg Prison Psychiatrist during the Nuremberg War Trials spoke at his 5th engagement for the Sunday Night forum. His topic was “How to Keep Young in Mind”. Dr. Ralph Bunch undersecretary of the United Nations and Nobel Peace prize winner spoke on “Toward a World Both Free and Peaceful”. Dana and Ginger Lambe noted explorers and authors presented a colored film entitled “The Lost Mission of Santa Ysabel”. The film was a documentation of their search for the mission and survival in the desert without food and water. The final session of the season was a film produced by Col. John Dl Craig which details the history of the Atomic Bomb.
  - Loose items, 1954-56 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Album 7, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    1956-1957 Season. The 2nd session of the season featured a debate on “Election Year Issues”. Speaking for the Democratic Party was Senator A.S. Monroney of Oklahoma and ex-governor of Arizona Howard Pyle (now deputy assistant to President Eisenhower), represented the Republican point of view. The debate was held at the Tucson High stadium because William R. Mathews President of Arizona State Board of Regents refused use of the University of Arizona Auditorium for a debate in which former Arizona Governor Pyle appeared. The traveling “World Affairs Council” a miniature U.N. Council appeared at the forum. Dean Rusk president of the Rockefeller Foundation and General Education Board spoke on the subject of “Unfinished Business in Our Foreign Affairs”. Jacques Cartier an inter-nationally known actor-dancer presented a one man show giving his own dramatic impersonation of notable historic figures which was entitled “Figures of Fire”. Dr. Ralph E. Lapp, nuclear scientist and director of Nuclear Science Services of Washington D.C. spoke about the changes in living through atomic science by the year 2000.
    1957-1958 Season. Frederick C. Othman a syndicated newspaper columnist who gave a lighter side to news from Capitol Hill. His topic was “Confusion on the Potomac”. Senator Barry Goldwater returned to the forum, his topic was “Report from Washington”. The Dublin Players return for their third appearance at the forum and performed the Bernard Shaw’s play “Arms and the Man”. Mrs. Eleanor Roosevelt returned to the forum for her second appearance the title of her lecture was “Russia the Country and People as I saw them”. Senator John F. Kennedy addressed the Sunday Night forum for the first time. The topic of his speech was “America’s Leadership Reappraised”. Dr. Margaret Mead well-known anthropologist spoke on the topic “Sex and Temperaments, Male and Female”. The final speaker of the season was Bishop Gerald Kennedy; head of the Methodist Church in the western area talk was entitled “Around the world in 30 Days”. He reported on his interviews with Korean President Rhee and India’s leader Nehru.
  - Loose items, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Album 8, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Season 1958-1959: Speaker, Marquis Childs was a news analyst and columnist, his topic was “Two-Party Politics and T-Party Responsibility”. Nelson Cruikshank director of the AFL-CIO Department of Social Security, Washington, D.C., spoke on “The Role of Government in Economic Security”. Dr. Fayez Sayeghy, counselor for the Arab States Delegations Office at the United Nations criticized the United States for its support of the nation of Israel. His topic was “The Arab World between East and West”. Abba Eban, Israel’s ambassador to the United States and the head of the Israel delegation the UN spoke on “Israel Amongst the Nations” stating that peace will come only from the voluntary impulse of will and not from outside pressures. Arizona Representative Steward Udall was a substitute for Senator Stuart Symington who canceled his appearance at the forum. Steward Udall’s subject for his speech was “Outlook for the 86th Congress”. He also criticized President’s Eisenhower’s federal budget and predicted Hawaiian Statehood. The Moral Rearmament presented the Phyllis Austin play “He Was Not There”. The message of the play was that men’s heart must change if world peace is to be achieved. Inez Robb one of the nation’s best known and favorite newspaper columnists spoke on “People and Places”. Miss Robb was a world traveling reporter, war correspondent and human interest writer. The final session for the 1958-1959 season included two travelogue films presented and narrated by Eric Pavel on the Philippines and Venezuela.
  - Loose items, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Album 9, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    1959-1960 Season opened with an address from Dr. Martin Luther King entitled “A Great Time to be Alive”. Dr. King discussed the challenge American faced in order to accomplish racial integration believing that within five years much of the present mass resistance would be gone. Arizona Governor Paul Fannin spoke on the topic “Changes and Challenges on the Arizona Scene”. Senator Hubert Humphrey from Minnesota and presidential hopeful for 1960 spoke at the Sunday Night. Bertha D. Adkins undersecretary for Health, Education, and Welfare lectured on the “New Horizons for the Aging”. Dr. W. Randolph Lovelace was a space medicine pioneer and the title of his speech was “Men in Space”. Mrs. Hjordis K. Parker returned for her 4th engagement at the forum and presented the film “Norway Changing and Changeless” Cecil Brown, chief of the National Broadcasting Company’s Far East staff spoke on “The Menace of Red China”. Avraham Harmoan, Israel ambassador to the United States the subject of his talk was “Israel and the Middle East”. Senator Stuart Symington from Missouri and an aspirating Democratic candidate for president spoke on “A Foreign Economic Policy on the Road to Peace”. This was John Goddard’s 2nd appearance at the forum. He narrated his film “Conquest of the Congo”. John Godard was the first white man to explore the entire length of the Congo River. The 1960-1959 Season concluded with John D. Craig who narrated the film “Family Holiday in Europe.
  - Loose items, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Album 10, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    1960-61 Season opened with Don Cooper who presented his color film the “Klondike! Highway to Alaska”. The 1st lecture of the season was given by Ron Landau an expert on North African affairs. His topic was “North Africa Friend or Foe of the West”. Dr. Milton Erickson, Phoenix psychiatrist, spoke on “The Medical Use of Hypnosis in Medicine”. William C. Sullivan chief assistant to J. Edgar Hoover discussed ‘Communism in the United States and the Western Hemisphere”. The Little Gaelic Singers of Ireland performed on the Forum’s patron recognition night. Dr. Khosro Khosrovay, minister of the Imperial Embassy of Iran in Washington, D.C. spoke on the “Economic Conditions in Iran”. Robert Davis presented “Arizona Utopia” a colorful travelogue he produced and narrated. The film included scenes of Mt. Lemmon, A Mountain, the UA Campus and Old Tucson. Margaret Mead made her 3rd appearance at the forum and discussed the topic “How Flexible is Human Nature?” A film produced on University of Arizona called “Campus International” was presented at the final forum of the 1960-61 Season.
  - Loose items, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Album 11, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    1961-1962 Season opened with Don Cooper, travel photographer and humorist. Cooper returned for his 3rd appearance and presented his new film entitled “Sourdoughs to Senoritas. Dr. Frank Laubach, founder of the “Each One Teach One” returned to forum and spoke on the topic “The Communist – Report on Southeast Asia”. Roscoe Drumond nationally known journalist and columnist discussed “The First Year of President Kennedy’s Administration.” Stewart Udall, Interior Secretary of State, addressed the forum on the topic “Conservation: the Quiet Crisis”. Arizona’s Republican Senator Barry Goldwater and Norman Thomas, six times presidential candidate on the Socialist ticket, debated on the subject of “Conservatism vs. Socialism. Curtis Nagel returned for his 8th appearance at the Sunday Night forum. He narrated his film “Road to Mandalay”. Senator John Tower of Texas, the only Republican Senator to be elected by a popular vote margin in Texas since the reconstruction, discussed “Conservatism in the South”. Dr. Martin Luther King spoke for a 2nd time at the Sunday Night forum his topic was “Stride Toward Freedom”. The film “Boldest Journey” a 40,000 miles odyssey through 24 countries of Europe, Asia and Africa was presented and narrated by John Goddard.
  - Loose items, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Album 12, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    1962-1963 Season. Highlights included the debate between U.S. Representative Morris K. Udall and John J. Rousselot, representative from California as well as a national officer in the John Brich Society. They debated on the topic “What is the best way to Fight Communism?” Richard Graham the associate director and chief of recruitment for the Peace Corps discussed “The Peace Crops, in Profile”. Conservative William F. Buckley debated liberal Sydney Lens on the subject “Is the Welfare State a Step Forward?” Columnist Abigail Van Buren, known as “Dear Abby” spoke at the forum on the topic “The Trouble I’ve Seen.” David Brinkley a NBC radio and television Correspondent, who had just finished his 6th season on the Huntley-Brinkley Report talked about the two myths from which the American public suffers. Victor Riesel, a national syndicated labor columnist who specialized in labor unions, told the forum audience that today’s labor leaders will be tomorrow’s prime ministers. A program of Indian culture was featured at the Sunday night forum with guest speaker Philleo Nash, commissioner of Indian Affairs for the U. S. Interior Department.
  - Loose items, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Album 13, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 3)